Guide to the Frank Baker Collection of Wesleyana and British Methodism, 1536-1996 and undated RL.00413
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Separately Cataloged Related Small Collections, 1701-1958 and undated, 12 boxes, 26 volumes
  - Thomas Burton papers, 1707-1731 [catalog record], 9 items
    Church of England. Diocese of York--History--18th century.
    Sermons, English--18th century
    Gunpowder Plot, 1605--Sermons
    Charles I, King of England, 1600-1649--Sermons
    - Volume I: twelve sermons prepared for publication, circa 1713-1721
      Contents include: No. 1: the 1713 Thanksgiving for peace sermon (Burton's only known publication); No. 2: A sermon on the martyrdom of King Charles I; No. 3: On Nov. 15, 1714, Thanksgiving for deliverance from Gunpowder Treason; No. 4: On the King's Accession, Aug. 1714, King George I; and eight other sermons on such topics as obedience to magistrates, "not peace, but a sword," rejoicing in persecution, plague fasts (1721) thanksgiving for deliverance from the plague, and one sermon on St. Thomas's day.
    - Volume II: Twelve sermons prepared for publication, undated
      Contents include: three sermons on death and judgment, three on the Resurrection, one on the Sabbath, one on Swearing, and one on partaking in the Lord's Supper.
    - Volume III: Twelve devotional sermons with an emphasis upon preparing for death, all preached at Halifax and dated, 1724-1731
    - Volume IV: Seventeen sermons, the first of which was prepared for publication, preached from 1707-1725
      Contents are mainly sermons upon Saints' Days, but also national occasions, including: St. Bartholomew's Day; two on Christmas Day; two on Trinity Sunday; John the Baptist; St. Matthias, Jan. 30 (i.e. King Charles the Martyr); the Purification; St. Matthew, St. Paul, St. Barnabas, St. Peter, and St. Philip; also "Preacht May 1, 1707, The day of Thanksgiving for Uniting the two Kingdoms of England and Scotland," and "On the Restauration" (i.e. of the Stuart family in 1660).
    - Volume V: Thirteen sermons prepared for publication, circa 1719-1726
      Many pages torn out, but remaining sermons include: No. 4, against fornication (1726); Nos. 5-7, teaching all nations (1719) (Baptism); and No. 8-13 on the Lord's Supper, of which parts of 8 and 10 are torn out.
    - Volume VI: remains of twelve sermons, undated
      Pp. 1-38, 49-62 torn out. Remaining contents include: part of No. 1; Nos. 5-7, on 1 Cor. 10:12, "take heed lest ye fall"; Nos. 8-10 on Matt. 11:28-30, "Come unto me"; and nos. 11-12 on Luke 12:33-4, "giving alms".
    - Volume VII: Thirteen sermons on devotional and ethical subjects from various scripture locations, with nos. 3, 7, and parts of 11 and 12 torn out, undated
    - Volumes VIII and IX: two volumes entitled An Exposition of the Church Catechism, for the Instruction of the Youth of Halifax Parish in the Diocese of York, by Thomas Burton, A.M.
      Further contents include: Vol. I contains an additional sermon to be placed between pp. 99-100, and Vol. II contains an additional sermon to be placed before p. 83.
  - Charles Clarke papers, circa 1699-1725 [catalog record], 2 items
    Sermons of Charles Clarke (b. circa 1660), vicar of Kirby-on-the-Moor, Yorkshire, England, 1693-1705, and rector of Hayley, Norfolk, 1700-1706. Two volumes of sermons, one of which cannot be positively identified as Clarke's. Both volumes date from the late 17th or early 18th centuries.
    Clarke, Charles.
    Sermons, English--18th century.
    - Volume I: inscribed on flyleaf: "Sum Ex Libris Caroli Clarke E Collegio Aenei Nasi, Oxon," and in another hand, "Mr. John Clarke his booke Anno 1725".
      Contents include sermons on the following texts: 1 Kings 10:9 (possibly about royal coronation); Matthew 5:6; 1 John 3:5; John 16:8.
    - Volume II: from same period, and apparently also from Yorkshire; probably (but not certainly) by Clarke.
      Contents include the following sermons: three sermons on Wisdom (Prov. 3:17); Christmas sermon on 1 Tim. 3:16; sermon on Gunpowder Plot Day, Nov. 5 using Prov. 21:30; two sermons preached July [16]99 at York on Ps. 4:6.
  - Sarah Crosby papers, 1760-1804 and undated [catalog record], 10 items
    Methodist preacher, of Leeds, Yorkshire, England. Letter book (1760-1774), six letters, and three other documents. Primarily outgoing correspondence on religion, particularly Methodism, plus memoranda, copies of letters between JW and Mary Bosanquet, and extracts from the diary of Jane Cooper. The two loose items are letters to Crosby from JW and Mary Bosanquet Fletcher.
    Includes a group of seven items related to the Sarah Crosby papers, according to a note by Baker; chiefly correspondence, transferred from the Frank Baker papers. See the individual notes for each item.
    Cooper, Jane--1738-1762.
    Fletcher, Mary Bosanquet.
    Wesley, John--1703-1791.
    Methodist Church--Great Britain--Clergy.
    Methodism. Women and religion--Great Britain.
    Women clergy--Great Britain.
    - Letter book, 1760-1774
    - Fletcher, Mary Bosanquet, Madeley, to Sarah Crosby, Leeds, 1804 Oct. 24
    - Wesley, John, Newcastle, to Sarah Crosby, n.p., 1780(?) May 11
    - Autograph letter signed to Mrs. C--n, 1777 Feb. 7
      Forms part of group of items found loose, together with two notes, probably by FB circa 1968, stating "Completion of Lot 58. The Letter Book of Sarah Crosby, bound, you do indeed have." Items cited below as signed are initialed "S.C." With one exception noted, all appear to be in same hand as materials previously cataloged as the Sarah Crosby Papers, 1760-1804.
    - Letter, unsigned, 1778 Feb. 25
    - Autograph letter signed, 1777 Mar. 27, 2 sheets
    - Letter, "My Dear Love...," unsigned and undated
    - "Instructions for Widows," unsigned and undated
    - Recipes for "Stomachic Pills" and "Aperient Pills," unsigned and undated [possibly in a different hand from items above]
  - Evelyn Milus Dixon Scrapbook, 1894-1956 [catalog record]
    Volume of autographs and sketches chiefly containing the signatures of leading British Methodists of the nineteenth and twentieth centuries and a number of missionaries.
    Dixon, Evelyn Milus.
    - Scrapbook assembled by Evelyn Dixon
  - James Gascoigne letter book, 1735-1747 [catalog record], 1 volume, 32 pages
    Contains copies of letters relating to the Hawk's participation in James Oglethorpe's expedition to Georgia, 1735-1736. Principal correspondents are Gascoigne and Oglethorpe. Correspondents also include naval officials in London, officers of ships on the expedition, and Hugh Mackay and others in Georgia. Topics include instructions and preparations for the trip, the voyage, activities on the Georgia coast, defenses against the Spanish, relations with the Spanish at St. Augustine and Hayana, settlements at Savannah, Frederica, Darien, and Cumberland Island in Georgia, and fort St. George, Fla. Also two letters, 1741 and 1747, concerning the expedition and Gascoigne after he left Georgia. Written in italic script.
    Inscribed inside the front cover: "Letters from Capt. Gascoigne of the Hawkes Sloop &c, Chiefly relating to his Attendance on Genl. Oglethorpe to Georgia, in 1735, 6 &c."
    Oglethorpe, James Edward, 1696-1785.
    Mackay, Hugh, ca. 1705-1763.
    Great Britain. Royal Navy--History--18th century.
    Georgia -- History--Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.
    Great Britain--Foreign relations--Spain.
    Spain--Foreign relations--Great Britain.
    Florida--History--Spanish colony, 1565-1763.
    - Letter book of James Gascoigne, captain of the British sloop-of-war Hawk
  - Thomas Illingworth diary, 1755-1759 [catalog record]
    Teacher, of Yeadon, Yorkshire, England. Diary kept by Illingworth during his service as a teacher in Yeadon, principally devoted to his spiritual life but also with references to the early Methodist movement in Yorkshire, theological issues of early Methodism, disputes between the Methodist societies and the Church of England parishes, the relationship of the Methodists to the Moravians, George Whitefield's Calvinistic theology, discipline problems in his school, and subject matter and classroom methods. Contains photocopy of manuscript, "On Illingworths of Addingham and Keighley," compiled by William I. Place.
    Whitefield, George--1714-1770.
    Church of England--Relations--Methodist Church.
    Moravian Church--England.
    Moravian Church--Relations--Methodist Church.
    Education--England.
    Methodist Church--England.
    Methodist Church--Relations--Anglican Communion.
    Methodist Church--Relations--Moravian Church.
    Schools--England--Yorkshire.
    Teachers--Diaries.
    Teachers--England.
    England--Religious life and customs.
    - Typescript; and notes on parish registers, 1755-1759, 1971-1977, and undated
      Materials include photocopied typescript of the Thomas Illingworth diary, 1755-1759. The author and thus the accuracy of this typescript is undetermined, although hand-written corrections may be in FB's hand; date of typescript is also uncertain, but attached correspondence indicates FB made this copy in 1971.
  - Perronet Family papers, 1752-1855 [catalog record], 10 items
    Collection comprises a scrapbook containing correspondence, reproductions of engravings, poetry, autographs, a pencil drawing, and an account of astrological incidents; there is also a small group of loose items. The correspondence is related to the Perronet family and other early leaders of the Wesleyan movement in England, and includes letters from Vincent Perronet stating his religious beliefs and moral principles, and letters from Charles Wesley to Peard Dickinson, Vincent's grandson-in-law, concerning doctrinal matters and family and personal subjects. Other correspondents include Sarah Wesley, Joseph Benson, Adam Clarke, James Dixon, Joseph Entwisle, John William Fletcher, Mary (Bosanquet) Fletcher, Thomas Jackson, Henry Moore, and Richard Watson. Loose items include a discourse by Charles Perronet on man's need for religion; diaries of an unidentified young woman commenting on sermons and spiritual life; and miscellaneous letters and autographs.
    Benson, Joseph--1749-1821.
    Clarke, Adam--ca 1762-1832.
    Dickinson, Peard--1758-1802.
    Dixon, James.
    Entwisle, Joseph--1767-1841.
    Fletcher, John--1729-1785.
    Fletcher, Mary--1739-1815.
    Jackson, Thomas.
    Moore, Henry--1751-1844.
    Perronet, Charles--ca 1723-1776.
    Perronet, Vincent--1693-1785.
    Watson, Richard--1737-1816.
    Wesley, Charles--1707-1788.
    Wesley, Sarah.
    Methodist Church--England--History.
    Women and religion--England.
    Women--Diaries.
    - Scrapbook (in page number order):
      - 3-19. Perronet, Vincent, to various family members, undated (7 items)
        [Attention: May need conservation prior to access.]
      - 21. Perronet, John, n.p., to ?, n.p., undated
      - 23. Wesley, John, Ireland, to Peard Dickinson, n.p., 1788 Apr. 27
      - 24-25. Wesley, John, Malton, to Peard Dickinson, n.p., 1790 June 21
      - 27. Wesley, John, Madeley, to Peard Dickinson, n.p., 1789 Mar. 23
      - 29. Briggs, Wm., Shoreham, to Betsey Briggs, n.p., 1767 Dec. 8
      - 31. Wesley, Charles, Bristol, to William Perronet, n.p., 1772 Jan. 23
      - 33. Wesley, Charles, Manchester, to William Perronet, n.p., 1756 Oct. 23
      - 35. Wesley, Charles, London (Marybone), to Betsey [Elizabeth] Briggs [Dickinson], London (Hoxton Square), [1787] Oct. 30
      - 37. Fletcher, John, Nyon, Switz., to Monsieur Perronet, Lausanne, Switz., 1780 Dec. 31
      - 39. Fletcher, John, London, to Monsieur Perronet, Nicon, Switz., 1778 June 2
      - 41. Bosanquet, Mary, n.p., to Vincent Perronet, n.p., 1765 Nov. 7
      - 43. Perronet, John, Margate, to Vincent Perronet, Shoreham, Kent, [?] Sept. 24
      - 45. Perronet, John, n.p., to Vincent Perronet, n.p., [?] Oct. 2
      - 47. Perronet, William, Shoreham, Kent, to Charles Wesley, Marybone, London, [1776] Aug. 22
      - 49. Perronet, Mrs., Shoreham, Kent, to Perronet's Niece (?), n.p., 1766 Jan. 4
      - 51. Briggs, John Hobart, Walworth, to His Sister, n.p., undated
      - 53. Briggs, Wm., Wakefield, to Betsey [Elizabeth] Briggs [Dickinson], London, 1815 Jan. 26
      - 55. Dickinson, Mrs., London (Hoxton Square), to Mrs. Houlson, Gloucestershire, 1793 Apr. 19
      - 57. Thompson, Mrs., n.p., to Mrs. Gray, n.p., 1807 Oct. 20
      - 59. Sells, Mrs., to ?, undated
      - 61. Gray, Mrs., n.p., to Her Daughter, Irene, London, undated
      - 63. Newton, John, London (Hoxton Square), to Irene Briggs, Shoreham, Kent, 1784, Sept. 11
      - 65. Benson, Joseph, Leeds, to Peard Dickinson, London (Hoxton Square), 1796 Dec. 17
      - 67. Benson, Joseph, Bristol, to Peard Dickinson, London (Hoxton Square), 1795 Oct. 8
      - 69. Benson, Joseph, Leeds, to Peard Dickinson, London (Hoxton Square), 1796 Mar. 17
      - 71. Wood, James, n.p., to Miss Perronet, n.p., July 1777
      - 73. Dixon, James, ?, to ?, n.p., 1848 Apr. 6
      - 75. Stanly, Jacob, to ?, undated
      - 77. Taylor, Joseph, n.p. (Trinity House Lane), to ?, n.p., 1845 Feb. 6
      - 79. Moore, Henry, Bath, to ?, London, 1804
      - 81. Entwisle, Joseph, Bristol (Old Market), to ?, Bristol (Stoke's Croft), 1827 Sept. 5
      - 83. Clarke, Adam, Manchester, to ?, n.p., 1804 July 16
      - 85. Wesley, Sarah [Sally], London (Nottingham Place), to Mrs. Dickinson, London (Hoxton Square), [?] June 11
      - 89. Watson, Richard, Leeds, to Rev. Warren, Walthamstow, 1830 Jan. 26
      - 91. Jackson, Thomas, London (Brunswick Place), to Mrs. Gray, Walthamstow, 1825 Oct. 4
    - Loose items
      - Briggs, William, n.p., to William Perronet, Bristol, 1752 Nov. 30
      - Constançon, H., Douay, to Father of Vincent Perronet, n.p., 1781 Nov. 26
      - Fletcher, John, Reading, to Vincent Perronet, Shoreham, Kent, 1777 Dec. 21
      - Wood, James, n.p., to Mrs. Gray, n.p., undated
      - Fletcher, John, Madeley, to Charles Perronet, London, 1772 Sept. 7
      - Leddey, T., Bath, verse, [?] Sept. 12
      - Galland, Thomas, Bath, verse, 1842 May 11
      - Perronet, Charles, "Some Ingenious Spiritual Thoughts," undated
      - Edith Thompson, obituary, Bath, undated
      - Autographs page, 1842 July 23
      - Pocket Book Almanack, London, 1853, 1855 (2 items)
      - Cooke, W. & G., London, Shoreham Church, Sussex, 1801 March 1
      - Portrait of Vincent Perronet--J. Spilsbury engraving after Sir Joshua Reynolds, undated
      - Memoirs of the Rev. Vincent Perronet, A.M., Late Vicar of Shoreham, in Kent, Methodist Magazine, 1799 Jan.-Apr.
  - H. B. Poole papers, 1910-1923 [catalog record], 6 items
    Records of attendance and membership for class meetings held by Methodist society near London. Records were kept by H. B. Poole.
    Church societies--England.
    Religious education--England.
    - Records of attendance
  - Isaac Watts papers, 1701-1788 [catalog record], 10 items
    Letter from Isaac Watts to a Mrs. Fay in Southampton, 1701 Apr. 15, expressing his sympathy on her recent widowhood and extending words of spiritual comfort. Other items in collection primarily written in a form of shorthand. Included are a sermon; extracts from the Bible, Genesis through Joel, and Amos through Acts; diaries of Sarah Ashurst containing spiritual reflections or discussion of theological points; and letter books of Joseph Parker, Watts's amanuensis, containing personal and business letters, and extracts from various works on topics such as faith, humility, friendship, etc.
    [Fragile; housed in Box OVSZ 2 in Frank Baker Collection of Wesleyana and British Methodism.]
    Watts, Isaac, 1674-1748.
    Diaries.
    Letter books.
    - Correspondence and other papers
  - George Whitefield papers, 1750-1768 [catalog record], 5 items
    Methodist clergyman and Evangelist from England who traveled to the U.S. and was a major influence in the "Great Awakening" religious revival in the U.S. Papers comprise a letter, 1750, discussing religious affairs in Georgia and South Carolina, the activities of James Habersham, and preaching missions to African Americans; a letter, 1759, to John Ryland, praising a young man for his Christian dedication; two letters, 1767 and 1768, to "My Dear M. Winter" in Bristol, and a short commentary on an unidentified passage from the Bible.
    Habersham, James--1715-1775.
    Ryland, John--1723-1792.
    African Americans--Religion.
    Methodist Church--Clergy--Correspondence.
    Methodist Church--Missions.
    Methodist Church--United States.
    Georgia--Religious life and customs.
    South Carolina--Religious life and customs.
    england--Religious life and customs.
    - Letters and a commentary
  - Elizabeth Woods papers, 1817-1830 [catalog record], 12 items
    Attendance records of a Sunday school class for girls in the Methodist society at Preston, England, taught by Elizabeth Woods. Several of the lists also include statements of financial contributions.
    - Attendance records